Saralee Hamilton Papers
Sophia Smith Collection
Saralee Hamilton papers
1911-2013
1972-2006
Hamilton, Saralee, 1945-2006
MS 629
17 boxes (9.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Feminist; Administrator; Reproductive rights advocate. Early records of the Reproductive Rights National Network, and materials documenting international women's rights organizing. Organizations and topics include the Reproductive Rights National Network, the Black Women's Health Project, Women's International Solidarity Affair in the Philippines (WISAP)/GABRIELA, MADRE, Women's Global Network for Reproductive Rights, sterilization abuse, reproductive rights advocacy and politics, lesbian and gay liberation, grassroots organizing, international women's rights, and rights for women laborers in the U.S. and in developing countries. Central American and Asian women's organizations are especially well- represented.
Saralee Mary Lamb Hamilton was born October 28, 1945. She was raised by her mother and grandparents in Glasgow, Pennsylvania. While studying for a B.A. at Dunbarton College of Holy Cross in Washington, DC, she was active in the National Federation of Catholic Students and worked on Barry Goldwater's 1964 presidential campaign. After a year of graduate work at New York University, Hamilton left for Philadelphia where, in 1968, she and a group of friends founded the Institute for Educational Development. The IED worked to facilitate communication between college students and administrators, and organized summer workshops and anti-Vietnam war activities.
In 1971, Hamilton was among the radical student activists who founded the New American Movement (NAM) to be a successor organization to Students for a Democratic Society (SDS). In 1973-74, she worked on NAM's efforts to impeach President Richard M. Nixon.
Hamilton joined the American Friends Service Committee (AFSC) in 1975 as founding director of its Nationwide Women's Program. NWP was one of AFSC's three "nationwide" programs (the Third World Coalition and Affirmative Action Office being the other two) established in the 1970s to "foster new ways of thinking (and working) across the entire AFSC so that members of oppressed and marginalized groups could participate fully in the life and work of the Service Committee." The "nationwides" were created to "heighten the awareness of organizational staff, and the effectiveness of organizational programming, at all levels."
In the early years of the program, Hamilton became part of the intellectual development of modern feminism, meeting often with the emerging leadership of that movement. According to a history of the Nationwide Women's Program written for the AFSC shortly after Hamilton's death, "Saralee, and most of those who have passed through the NWP as staff or committee members, have shared a bottom-line understanding of the crucial importance of intersectionality--analytically, programmatically, and politically." It was through Hamilton's efforts that various AFSC programs became connected to women's groups around the world, such as MADRE; GABRIELA, in the Philippines; Isis International Women's Information and Communication Service, in South America; and Women Living Under Muslim Laws. She was also involved in the Reproductive Rights National Network (R2N2), and in the Committee to End Sterilization Abuse (CESA). Her vision of mutuality introduced AFSC perspectives to women's movements, and brought learnings from those movements to the AFSC. She was also adept at fostering women's involvement in issues from the policy level down to the every day actions that could bring about change. She organized delegations to women's conferences including the U.N. World Conferences on Women in Nairobi, Kenya, in 1985, and in Beijing in 1995.
Saralee Hamilton died at age 61 on December 7, 2006 in Philadelphia, PA, of complications from cancer.
The Saralee Hamilton Papers consist of 9.5 linear ft. and are almost exclusively related to her activism and professional life, 1973 to 2006. Types of materials include brochures, correspondence, fact sheets, minutes, newsclippings, newsletters, notes, photographs, press releases, publications, reports, journal and newspaper articles, transcripts of interviews, and audio and videotapes.
Subjects at the heart of Hamilton's activism are all well documented, including sterilization abuse; reproductive rights advocacy and politics; lesbian and gay liberation; grassroots organizing; international women's rights; rights for women laborers, women and the impact of economic development; war's impact on women; indigenous women; women of color; the intersectionality of race, class, and gender; and religious organizations working on women's issues.
Conference and organization files document Hamilton's commitment to forging connections among women around the world through work with such groups as the international feminist network Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN/MUDAR), the General Assembly Binding Women for Reforms, Integrity, Equality, Leadership and Action (GABRIELA) in the Philippines, Isis International Women's Information and Communication Service, and the Women's Global Network for Reproductive Rights.
Organization files also document Hamilton's involvement with U.S. national organizations Coalition for Abortion Rights and Against Sterilization Abuse (CARASA), extensive files documenting the Reproductive Rights National Network (R2N2).
In addition to national and transnational activism, Hamilton's local work is also documented through organization files for such groups as NARAL Pennsylvania and Philadelphia Reproductive Rights Coalition, and subject files on reproductive rights in Pennsylvania and the women's movement in Philadelphia.
This collection is organized into seven series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS
II. ORGANIZATIONS
III. CONFERENCES
IV. RESOURCES
V. SUBJECT FILES
VI. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS AND ARTIFACTS
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following exceptions: Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Original audiovisual recordings have been transferred to digital format for research use.
Saralee Hamilton's colleague at the American Friends Service Committee Maria Pappalardo donated Hamilton's Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2007 and 2009.
American Friends Service Committee; Hamilton, Saralee, 1945-2006; National Black Women's Health Project; Reproductive health - History - Sources; Reproductive rights - History -- Sources; Reproductive Rights National Network; Sterilization (Birth control) -- United States -- History; Women -- Latin America; Women and peace -- South Asia; Women's rights -- Asia, Southeastern -- History -- Sources; Women's rights -- Developing countries
Related materials can be found in the Reproductive Rights National Network Records. The newsletter of the AFSC Nationwide Women's Program, Listen Real Loud, is in the SSC's periodicals collection.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS 1977-2006, undated, .5 linear ft.
  The small amount of biographical material consists of obituaries and remembrances written after Hamilton's death in 2006. The photographs primarily document conferences and demonstrations, including the 1977 National Women's Conference in Houston, the NOW March for Women's Equality/Women's Lives in 1989, and the Fourth World Conference on Women in Beijing, China, in 1995. Additional biographical information can be found in the history of Nationwide Women's Program in the American Friends Service Committee files in SERIES II. ORGANIZATIONS.
- SERIES II. ORGANIZATIONS 1972-2006, undated, 2.5 linear ft.
  Organizations files consist of brochures, fact sheets, flyers, minutes, newsclippings, newsletters, press releases, publications, reports, and statements. In some cases there is a small amount of correspondence between Hamilton and the organization. Some of the larger files, such as those documenting Reproductive Rights National Network (R2N2), General Assembly Binding Women for Reforms, Integrity, Equality, Leadership and Action (GABRIELA) and Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN--aka MUDAR), include minutes, notes, and conference and meeting materials. Of particular interest, are the transcripts of interviews about women's peace camps in the AFSC files and the extensive files related to R2N2.
- SERIES III. CONFERENCES 1975-2008, undated, 1.25 linear ft.
  Conference files consist of minutes, reports, press releases, programs, announcements, official declarations, packets, and publications from national and international conferences related to women and women's issues. They are arranged chronologically.
- SERIES IV. RESOURCES 1966-2005, undated, .75 linear ft.
  Materials in this series consist of bibliographies, brochures, case studies, curricula, facilitator guides, fact sheets, information kits, resource guides, and publications. They are arranged alphabetically by title.
- SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES 1911, 1955-2005, undated, 2.75 linear ft.
  Subject files contain booklets, brochures, fact sheets, flyers, newsclippings, papers, publications, reports, and statements. Particularly well documented are materials related to women's reproductive health and rights. They are arranged alphabetically by subject.
- SERIES VI. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS 1973-2006, undated, 1.5 linear ft.
  This series consists of slide presentations, audiotapes, videotapes, and DVDs on many of the same subjects as are represented elsewhere in the papers. Original audio and video is closed to research use. MP4 use copies are available for some titles as noted in the container list. Consult SSC staff for more information. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual materials for which there is no use copy should contact the Sophia Smith Collection to discuss options.
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS .25 linear ft.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Biographical materials 2006-13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Seditious Delicious #2 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs
    - Generalundated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Album (disassembled), National Women's Conference, Houston, and Technical Worker's Conference [AFSC?] 1977 (Box 1)
      - Photocopy of album (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Prints removed from album (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
      - Prints not used in album 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Negatives (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Abortion Rights Action Week, Philadelphia 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - World Conference to Review and Appraise the Achievements of the U.N. Decade for Women, Nairobi, Kenya, 1985; Kapatiran ConferenceSep, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - March for Women's Equality/Women's Lives, Washington, DC9 Apr 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Fourth World Conference on Women, Beijing, China 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- SERIES II. ORGANIZATIONS
  - Abortion Rights Coalition (ARC)undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Abortion Rights Committee (ARC)undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Abortion Rights Movement of Women's Liberation (ARM) 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Alliance Against Women's Oppression (AAWO) 1982-84 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - American Friends Service Committee (AFSC)
    - General 1974-2004, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Abortion Rights Action WeekOct 1979
      - General and organizers' packet (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Publications (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Reproductive Rights packetcirca 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Nationwide Women's Program (NWP)
      - General 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - "Lesbians Speak to the AFSC" packetcirca 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Peace camps research for "Is a women's peace movement taking root?" in AFSC Women's Newsletter, volume 6, number 1, winter 1985
      - Background information 1983-84 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Women's Encampment for a Future of Peace and Justice, Seneca Army Depot 1983-85, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Interviews (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
    - Songbooks 1975, 1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Asian Women's Human Rights Council (AWHRC), Courts of Women 2000-01 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Asociacion de Mujeres de El Salvador (AMES) 1984-85 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Center for Women's Resources (CWR), Philippines 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chicago Women's Liberation Union 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Coalition Against Sterilization Abuse (CASA)undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Coalition for Abortion Rights and Against Sterilization Abuse (CARASA)
    - General 1978-83, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Publication, "Women Under Attack"1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Comite de Unidad Campesina, Guatemalacirca 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Concern for Health Options: Information, Care and Education (CHOICE) 1974-79 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Delegation of Original Women of Philadelphia (DOWOP) 1994 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN) (aka MUDAR)
    - General 1989-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - DAWN Informs newsletter 1987-94 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Feminists in Solidarity with the Central American and Caribbean People 1986-87 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General Assembly Binding Women for Reforms, Integrity, Equality, Leadership and Action (GABRIELA), Philippines
    - General 1988-92, undated (Box 3, Folder 4-7)
    - Women's Solidarity Affair in the Philippines/Pacific (WISAP) 1986-91 (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
  - Gabriela Network (GABNet): Sisters in Support Across the Pacific, New York (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Germantown Women's Center 1973-75 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Homeland Ministries 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Indochina Peace Campaign 1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - International Women's Development Agency 1988-89 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Isis International Women's Information and Communication Service
    - General 1980-2000 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Annual reports 1992, 2000-01 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Information packet "Women's Action for the Environment," circa 1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Publications 1984-94 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ladies Against Womencirca 1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - MADRE 1999-2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Las Mujeres de las Colonias en el Movimiento Urbano Popular, Mexicoundated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National Abortion Rights Action League Pennsylvania (NARAL)
    - General 1978-80, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Linelines newsletter 1978-81 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - National Black Women's Health Project (NBWHP)
    - General 1983-93, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Self-Help Group Development in Nigeria"1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - National Campaign to Restore Abortion Funding 1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - National Committee on Pay Equity 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW) 1986-2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - National Woman's Party 1979-85 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - National Women's Health Network (NWHN) 1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - New American Movement (NAM) 1977-81 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Philadelphia Black Women's Health Project 1983-90 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Philadelphia Reproductive Rights Coalition 1978-81, undated (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - Philadelphia Reproductive Rights Organization
    - General 1981-84, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Publications 1981-83 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Philadelphia Women's Liberation Center 1972-73 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Planned Parenthood 1979-2003 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RCAR) 1982-88 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice 2005 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Religious Network for Equality for Women, Women's Collective 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Reproductive Rights National Network (R2N2)
    - General 1979-84, undated (Box 5, Folder 3-8)
    - Grant proposalcirca 1980 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - National Conference
      - ChicagoSep 1980 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - New York CityMar 1981 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - San FranciscoNov 1981 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - ChicagoNov 1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - East Coast Regional MeetingApr 1982 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - "In Support of Women's Lives" protest, Cherry Hill, NJ17 Jul 1982 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Population control slideshow 1981-83 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Sistren Theatre Collective, Jamaica
    - General 1986-90 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Publications 1985-87, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sojourner Truth Organizationcirca 1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - South and Meso American Indian Information Center (SAIIC) 1991-96 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Third World Movement Against the Exploitation of Women (TW MAE-W)circa 1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Women Against the Warundated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Women's Global Network for Reproductive Rights
    - General 1985-97 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Maternal Morbidity 1988-2003 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Women's Human Rights International Association (WHRIA) 1996 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Women's International Resource Exchange (WIRE)circa 1981 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Women's Rights Network, Boston 1977 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Women's Skills and Resource Exchange 1987-88, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Women's Support Group of the Wai'Anae Coast, Hawai'i 1980-91 (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
  - World Federalist Association, Gender Equity Commission 2002 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- SERIES III. CONFERENCES
  - World Conference of the International Women's Year, Mexico City 1975: declaration and plans of action (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Mid-Decade World Conference of the United Nations Decade for Women, Copenhagen, Denmark 1980: Focus on Palestinian Women (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Women Hold Up Half the Sky: Perspectives on Women and Development, Manitoba15-16 Oct 1982 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Women's Gathering, Washington, DC24-26 Aug 1983 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - International Tribunal and Meeting on Reproductive Rights, Amsterdam22-28 Jul 1984: report, "Divided in Culture, United in Struggle" World Conference to Review and Appraise the Achievements of the UN Decade for Women, Nairobi, Kenya, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - World Conference to Review and Appraise the Achievements of the UN Decade for Women, Nairobi, Kenya, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Preparation
      - General (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - "The Challenge of Nairobi: Learning From the Past to Build a Better Future" the Report of the National Consultative Committee: Planning for Nairobi"Mar 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Transcripts of conversations Charlotte Bunch, Betty Powell, and Barbara Smith about lesbians attending the Conference 1985 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - General (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Forward-Looking strategies (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - U.N. Report of Conference15 Sep 1985 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - National Conference on Women and Organizing, Stony Point, New York16-18 Feb 1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Women and Development: The Effects of Militarization, Labrador5-7 May 1989 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Women's World Congress for a Healthy Planet, Miami, Florida8-12 Nov 1991 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Region III, U.S. Official Preparatory Meeting for the United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women5 Aug 1994 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - International Conference on Population and Development, Cairo, 5-13 Sep 1994
    - General 1994 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - ICPD + 5, Five-year review and appraisal of Implementation of the ICPD Programme of Action 2006 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - 39th Session of the U.N. Commission on the Status of Women, Final Preparatory Meeting for the Fourth World Conference on Women15 Mar-4 Apr 1995 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Fourth World Conference on Women, Beijing, China 1995
    - General (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Preparatory meetings, conferences, and statements (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Declaration and Platform for Action
      - 1994- Jun 1995 (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
      - Jul-Dec 1995, undated (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Disabled women (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Government commitments (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - International Network of Women of Color 1994-95 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Latina Rights Initiative (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Lesbians (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Press conferences, releases, statements (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Statements to the Conference and NGO Forum (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Non-Governmental Organizations (NGO) Forum
      - General (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Declaration of Indigenous Women (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Reflections and workshop summaries by Kathy Bond- Stewart and Talent Nyathi (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Reports
        - Final report (Box 8, Folder 13)
        - Vietnamese delegation (Box 8, Folder 14)
        - Women and homelessness (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - "Building on Beijing: United States NGOs Shape a Women's National Action Agenda"1996 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - "Women Connecting Beyond Beijing" A workshop in response to the United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women, Facilitator's Guide by Maria Riley, English and Spanish editions 1996 (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
  - Frontline Feminisms: Women, War & Resistance, University of California Riverside Center for Women in Coalition16-18 Jan 1997 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Women of Color in the Workplace Conference, Fellowship of Reconciliation, Atlanta, GA14-16 Nov 1997 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Transforming Women's Careers, Women's Studies, University of Hawai'i at Manoa6-7 Mar 1998 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - National Black Religious Summit III on Sexuality, Black Church Initiative and Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice, Washington, DC7-9 Jul 1999 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Beijing + 5 Review 2000 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - United Nations World Conference Against Racism, Racial Discrimination, Xenophobia, and Related Intolerance, (WCAR) Durban, South Africa31 Aug-8 Sep 2001 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Re-Inventing Globalization, AWID International Forum (Association for Women's Rights in Development), Guadalajara, Mexico3-6 Oct 2002 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1982-2006, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
- SERIES IV. RESOURCES
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "Beyond ERA: A Women's Agenda for Nevada," Nevada Public Affairs Review 1983 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "Celebrating Labor Union Women's History," by Marjorie H. Stern, Coalition of Labor Union Women 1987 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "Defending Reproductive Rights: An Activist Resource Kit," Political Research AssociatesNov 2000 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "Economics: Women's Cry for Change," National Assembly of Women Religious resource packet 1987 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - "Empowering Women Through Research Networking" conference report, Center for Women's ResourcesSep 1987 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - "Global Feminist Perspectives on Reproductive Rights and Reproductive Health: A Report on the Special Sessions Held at the Fourth International Interdisciplinary Congress on Women, Hunter College, New York City," by Rosalind P. Petchesky and Jennifer A. Weiner 1990 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - "Homeless Women: Creating Community, Creating Change, a 'How To' Skills with a Feminist Perspective resource packet, National Assembly of Religious Women 1989 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - "Liberation of Women: Sexual Repression and the Family" by Laurel Limpus, New England Free Pressundated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "More on the Political Economy of Women's Liberation" by Mickey Ellinger and John Rowntree, Bay Area Radical Education Project, reprint of a 1970 article (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - National Young Women's Day of Action organizing packet 1997 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "Philadelphia Women's Yellow Pages"1995-96, 2003, 2004-05 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "Picking Up the Pieces: Women in and out of Work in the Rural South," Highlander Research and Education CenterJan 1986 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Pink Pages: The Lesbian and Gay Community Phone Book, New York City 1992 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "The Political Economy of Women's Liberation" by Margaret Benston, New England Free Press, reprint of a 1969 article, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 7)